Do I understand correctly that Moscow is now
я правильно понимаю что Москва сейчас
feeding Tatarstan,
кормит Татарстан
well, not Moscow, but the rest of Russia,
ну не Москва но остальная Россия
oh, hello, I didn't recognize you by your surroundings,
о привет я тебя по антуражу не узнал
hello, how are you doing, are you in a
привет какие дела у вас так это ты в
new house or in a new
новой хате или в новом
city or just in another room, after all, I understand, I understand, we have
городе или просто в другой комнате всё
n't talked for a long time,
же а понял понял давно-давно не общались
let's talk,
давай пообщаемся
how are you and Trump doing,
как там у вас с Трампом дела
yes, Trump, you see, Trump is an ally of the
да Трамп видишь Трамп короче союзник
Russian Federation, now the
Российской Федерации теперь теперь
Chinese are for us, like the Americans are for you, the Chinese
китайцы за нас типа американцы за вас
Why are the Chinese for you, well, China, yes,
китайцы Почему китайцы за вас ну Китай
China has clearly stated that Europe and
да Китай чётко заявил да что Европа и
Ukraine should be at the
Украина должны быть за столом
negotiating table, like he says that there can't
переговоров типа он говорит что не не
be a deal on Ukraine, yes, a
может быть сделки по Украине да
peaceful one, only between the US and Russia, that's all, so
мирной только между США и Россией всё
China is now with us,
так что Китай теперь с нами
well, don't look at the Chinese, everything is very clearly
ну китайщем не смотри всё очень чётко
emerging, Trump is showing everyone that
вырисовывается трамп всем показывает что
he is friends with Russia, but not friends with
он дружит с Россией да не дружит с
Canada, not friends with Europe, not friends with
Канадой не дружит с Европой не дружит с
Mexico, not friends with China, he has
Мексикой не дружит с Китаем он их мыто
imposed duties on them, how is it called in Russian, yes, myto, yes, myto, yes, that is
как это по-русски мыто пошлинами обложил
real now, and here,
да то есть реально сейчас да ещё и вот
ola, Russia is emerging, and that you just
ола вырисовывается Россия и что просто
know  when was this marshal's plan
знаешь когда вот этот план маршала был
after the war how marshal how many 12
после войны как маршала у сколько там 12
billion dollars America drank in Europe
млрд долларов Америка бухала в Европу
Europe raised its standard of living there
европа подняла свой уровень жизни там
expanded production and in
развела и в
general all of Europe here they conducted an analysis of the
общем-то вся Европа вот провели анализ
growth of the economy GDP Europe America and
роста экономики ВВП Европа Америки и
China
Китая
only America demonstrated constant growth all the time
только Америка демонстрировала всё время
Europe like that with the jocks
постоянный рост европа вот так с качками
jumping sometimes it overtook America then
прыгала то она перегоняла Америку то
on the contrary it lagged behind then quickly caught up
она наоборот отставала потом догоняла
but so what is this at all in the
быстро но так к чему это вообще вот в
fourteenth year the US GDP is 15
четырнадцатом году ВВП США составляет 15
trillion dollars and the European Union 14
трилн долларов а Европейского Союза 14
trillion now the situation America 30
триллин сейчас ситуация Америка 30
trillion Europe 20 so what are you
триллионов Европа 20 так к чему ты
getting at I don't understand at all what
ведёшь я что-то вообще не понял к чему
this conversation is at all well this is like
вообще этот разговор ну это как бы
skimming the fat of this bull that
обезжиривают бычка вот этого которого
was poured money into
вбухали денег в
Europe and Ukraine is like a
Европу а Украина - это как
tool so that Europe spends money
инструмент чтобы Европа тратила деньги
on Ukraine fought with
на Украину воевала с
Russia and so stop wait stop uh come on
Россией и так стоп подожди стоп ээ давай
again earlier you said that
так ещё раз раньше вы рассказывали что
we are a puppet of the United States
мы марионетка Соединённых Штатов
you are all a puppet so stop wait no well
вы всех марионетка так стоп подожди не
who controls us the United
ну кто кто нами управляет Соединённые
States or Europe  let's decide and you in
Штаты или Европа давай определись а вы в
joint use as in joint
совместном пользовании как в совместном
use that here are the frictions between Europe
пользовании тот вот тёрки между Европой
and the USA they came with Trump friction well who and
и США они с Трампом пришли тёрки ну кто
who now in short who is our puppeteer
да кто сейчас короче кто наш кукловод
Europe or the USA it's
европа или США
not hard to say both of them no well how
не сложно сказать и те и те не ну как
look they just had a fight they now
смотри они сейчас поругались они сейчас
they now or rather they didn't even have a fight it's
они сейчас вернее они даже не поругались
Zelensky Zelensky's main mistake was
Зеленский главная ошибка Зеленского была
that he spoke in English
что он говорил на английском языке
he doesn't know English well he used the wrong
английский он знает плохо он использовал
words that needed to be
не те слова которые надо было
used in America in the English
использовать в америка в английском
language there are a lot of different words they need to be used and which ones we have
языке много всяких слов их надо испо а
one word and they have
которые вот у нас одно слово а у них там
five words for example what word did they
пять слов например какое слово они так
use like that for the sake of interest well I watched
использовал ради интереса ну я смотрел
Sanya in Florida who has bloggers there
Саню во Флориде который есть там блогеры
and he says that here he says this
и он говорит что вот он говорит это
word what exactly what word I I don't
слово какое конкретно какое слово я я не
remember I don't know English well you don't
помню я плохо английский знаю ты же
know English well no well you remembered some words
плохо знаю не ну ты же слова какие-то
Trump Trump kind of took it that
запомнил трамп Трамп как бы воспринял
Zelensky So look in short
это что Зеленский Так то смотри короче
let's do this who is now the bigger puppeteer of
давай так кто сейчас больше кукловодит
Russia Ukraine the USA or Europe
Россией Украиной США или Европа
we have now probably more Europe
у нас сейчас наверное больше Европа
got the question well here  Zelensky Zelensky
понял вопрос ну вот Зеленский Зеленский
had a row with the country well look if
поругался со стра да ну смотри есть если
we yes if we are still puppets of the USA
мы да если всё-таки мы марионетки США
why is the USA disconnecting our intelligence why is the
зачем США нам отключает разведны зачем
USA suspending aid to us
США нам помощь приостанавливает
well Biden's course has changed the Democrats then that
ну изменился курс Байдена демократы то
means that we are not puppets of the USA we are
значит всё то мы не марионетки США мы
only puppets of Europe now
только марионетки Европы теперь
and the Munroe Doctrine have you heard anything about it
а доктрина Манро слышал что-нибудь о ней
look again Munro is even shorter damn
ещё раз смотри манро - это ещё короче
last like last century yes yes here
блин прошлый типа прошлый век да да вот
Trump is returning to the doctrine this is no
Трамп возвращается к доктрине это нет
look you will read this they drove around in
смотри это ты прочитаеш это гоняли в
some Russian Telegram channel yes what is
каком-то русском Telegram-канале да что
he talking about control of the two Americas all there is no
он про контроль двух Америк всё никакой
smell of the Monroe Doctrine at all what is the
там доктрины Монроя не пахнет вообще в
essence of the Munroe Doctrine it was that no
чём суть доктрины Манро было что ни одна
European side interferes in the
европейская сторона не всовывается в
affairs of the American continent of North
дела американского континента Северной
America and South America but they but they do not
Америки и Южной Америки но они но они не
meddle in other continents USA wait
лезут в другие континенты США подожди
wait stop what Americans what
подожди стоп какие амери какие
European countries meddle in American
европейские страны лезут в американские
countries
страны
while no one but America refuses to intervene
пока их никто но Америка отказывается
Wait again look again you
вме Подожди ещё раз ещё раз смотри ты
say that Trump is returning to the
говоришь что Трамп возвращается к
doctrine  Monroe, according to which Europe does not
доктрине Монро по которой Европа не
interfere in the countries of South and North America,
лезет в страны Южной и Северной Америки
yes, like
да типа
Americaniti, tell me Europe, Europe interferes in at least
американти скажи мне Европа Европа хоть
one country in South or North America,
в одну страну Южной или Северной Америки
no, but America has been interfered with everywhere
нет ну зато Америку залезли везде где
possible,
только можно
God, America, and that is, in short, in general, that
боже Америка и То есть короче в общем то
is, the Munroe Doctrine is generally useless,
есть доктрина Манро вообще ни к чему
why is this such a rehabilitation of the
ну почему это такое реабилитация
Munroe Doctrine in the Trump version and
доктрины Манро в трамповской версии и
Trump, Trump, he says to Zelensky:
Трамп Трамп он говорит вот Зеленскому:
"What's the big deal, he says: "We
"В чём сырбор говорит: "Мы на вас
spent 350 billion dollars on you, where is our
потратили 350 млрд долларов где наши
money, return our money, we see that
деньги верните наши деньги мы видим что
you are not winning and we see no point in
вы не побеждаете и мы не видим смысла
spending more money on you, so give us
больше на вас тратить деньги вот
your resources, what do you have,
отдавайте свои ресурсы что у вас есть
look, let's finish with the
смотри давай так давай закончим с
Munroe Doctrine, let's finish with the
доктриной Манро давай закончим с
Munroe Doctrine, the US is present in Iraq,
доктриной Манро сша присутствует в Ираке
yes, the US is present in Syria,
да сша присутствует в Сирии
but what Monroe Doctrine are we
только про какую доктрину Монро мы
talking about, well, they will gradually
говорим ну они будут потихоньку
wind down,
сворачиваться
that is, the US, they, you know,
то есть США они они понимаешь
wait, stop, do I understand correctly, the US will
подожди стоп я правильно понимаю США
now withdraw from the territories in which
сейчас уйдёт от территорий на которых
it essentially de facto controls
она по сути де-факто контролирует добычу
oil production, it will simply withdraw now  yes
нефти просто уйдёт сейчас да
no it will pump oil it will pump
нет она будет качать нефть будет качать
resources but political influence military
ресурсы но политическое влияние военное
influence will be at a minimum and how
влияние будет на минимуме а как она
will it pump if then tomorrow the
будет качать если там тогда завтра
locals take it like and seize power they will
местные возьмут типа и захватят власть
not take it there will be troops left but they
не возьмут там останутся войска но они
will sit quietly and that is to say the troops will
будут сидеть тихо а то есть войска
remain after all no
останутся всё-таки никакая доктрина
Munroe doctrine like yes but they will not go there
Манро типа да но они не полезут там
let's say somewhere there are others in short
допустим куда-нибудь там другие короче
look in general this is a return of the
смотри в общем это возвратом доктрины
Munroe doctrine in short some of your bloggers
Манро это короче какие-то ваши блогеры
started to drive such and you all are
начали гонять такую а вы все
dragging apart the question you tell me look
растаскиваете вопрос ты мне скажи смотри
you tell me come on like this earlier you all kept
ты мне скажи давай так раньше вы все
telling us Russians that America is your
толдычили нам россияне что Америка ваш
main enemy yes America America now
главный враг да америка америка сейчас
what is the status of America for you
какой статус Америки для вас
yes none you understand it acts in the
да никакой понимаешь он действует в
interests of its Nazi so come on yes the USA
интересах своей наци так вот давай да
for you now is an enemy friend who is cunning
сша для вас сейчас враг друг кто
cunning calculating USA well
хитрый хитрый расчётливый США ну вот
look I just heard that Putin
смотри я просто слышал что там Путин
proposed to Trump together so that America would
предложил Трампу вместе чтобы Америка
mine aluminum in Russia and
добывала алюминий в России да
develop the Arctic yes what do you think is
разрабатывала Арктику да как ты считаешь
this a bending over to America or not  Putin
это есть прогиб перед Америкой или нет
needs to come to an agreement with someone,
путину надо с кем-то договориться
that is, Putin is
то есть Путин ради того чтобы с кем-то
ready to give his resources to
договориться готов отдать свои ресурсы
America in order to come to an agreement with someone, I understood correctly,
Америке я правильно понял
but he does not give them to them, he is trying to extract
но он им не отдаёт он пытается выудить
technology from them so that they can build their
технологии чтобы они построили свои
factories so that they can transfer them there. So stop, stop,
заводы чтобы они передали там Так стоп
stop, stop, look again, until
стоп стоп стоп ещё раз смотри до
2014, the Americans and Europeans
четырнадцатого года американцы европейцы
really built factories with you and
реально строили у вас заводы да там
extracted there and so on and so forth,
добывали и так дальше вс всё остальное
and then you decided that you were going the way
да потом вы решили что вы идёте путём
that you want to stop being a raw materials
что вы хотите перестать быть сыревым
appendage, you want a special
придатком вы хотите там у вас особый
path for everything there, and now everything is returning to the
путь всё а теперь всё возвращается к
fact that you are asking
тому что вам вы просите чтобы
American factories to come to you, it is
американские заводы пришли к вам
quite possible, I dont know, but whats the
вполне возможно не знаю так а в чём
joke, you
прикол
see, when Putin annexed Crimea,
понимаешь когда Путин присоединил Крым
he did not think that there would be such a
он не думал что будет такая реакция
wild reaction in the West,
дикая на Западе
he thought that somehow they had agreed on everything
он думал что там как-то всё договорились
there, he would swallow it all, they didnt swallow it
там проглотит это всё не проглотили
at all, look at our very first
вообще вот посмотри самое самую первую
conversation, which was in December of
нашу беседу которая в декабре двадцать
22, I immediately told you, you
второго года я тебе сразу сказал ты
hid it somewhere, take it out there, there
куда-то её спрятал вот вынь там 130.000
were 130,000 views, and on  I told you right away on YouTube
просмотров было а на Ютбе я тебе сразу
: "And how will you pay
сказал: "А чем вы будете расплачиваться
for this
за этот
lens?"  And so you return to the situation, I even
ленс?" И вот вы ситуации верну я я даже
said that you will climb on the Kursk NPP
сказал что вы на Курскую АЭС полезете
when you understand that you will not win and will not
когда поймёте что вы не победите и не
get through, yes, listen, you are a prophet,
пролезете да слушай ты вообще пророк
I see, well, you find it, so stop, stop, stop,
прямо я смотрю ну ты найди это так стоп
well, come on, tell me, the Russian
стоп стоп а ну давай скажи Российская
Federation will fall apart,
Федерация распадётся
no, why are you here, because it
нет вот тут ты почему потому что
will fall apart, and I will meet you and say:
распадётся и я тебя встречу и скажу:
"Look, remember, I told you on
"Смотри помнишь я тебе говорил седьмого
March 7, 2025, that the Russian
7 марта 2025 года что Российская
Federation will fall apart, but even when I
Федерация распадётся но даже когда я
told you this, I did not think that it would be
тебе это говорил я не думал что это
so powerful and so many
будет так мощно и настолько много
states," that's how I will tell you, I do
государств" вот так я тебе скажу
n't think that this will happen, well,
я не думаю что такое случится ну
all the national republics will
все национальные республики они
not feed themselves economically, yes, and
экономически себя не прокормят да да а
America will not feed anyone, yeah, that's
Америка кормить никого не будет угу вот
all, and it will not feed you, I mean,
и всё и вас кормить не будет в смысле
so wait, I understand correctly that
так подожди я Я правильно понимаю что
Moscow is now feeding Tatarstan,
Москва сейчас кормит Татарстан
well, not Moscow, but the rest of Russia, well,
ну не Москва но остальная Россия ну как
look, Tatarstan is really good, Tatarstan,
смотри Татарстан реально доба татарстан
Tatarstan provides for itself, by the way,
татарстан себя обеспечивает кстати
a little bit,
немножко
let's do it this way, Tatarstan will
то давай так то Татарстан будет
function normally, but
нормально функционировать так а вот
Bashkiria will not  will be fine and
Башкирия не будет нормально и
Bashkartastan yes why not and she asks
Башкартастан да почему нет а она просит
she is a subsidized region not look so here is the
она дотационный регион не вот смотри так
trap why no how why is
вот ловушка в чём поче нет как почему
she a subsidized region because they
она дотационный регион потому что
take taxes to the federal budget and
забирают налоги в федеральный бюджет а
some taxes to the local budget and
некоторые налоги в местный бюджет да и
then part of it is returned from the federal
потом часть из федерального возвращает
so if they don't take federal taxes at all
так если не будет вообще федеральные
yes Bashneft was re-registered it was
забирать да башнефть перерегистрировали
local yes it was
она она была местная да её
re-registered to Moscow and it
перерегистрировали на Москву и она
pays taxes to Moscow that's the
платит налоги в Москву вот в чём и
trick that's all I don't know what because of this
фишка вот и всё я не пол что из-за этого
Yes yes everything is like that look all the businesses yes no more
Да да всё так смотри все бизнесы да нет
look all the businesses yes large all the
ещё смотри все бизнесы да крупные все
network they are all registered in
сетевые они все зарегистрированы в
Moscow yes Moscow St. Petersburg that's all and so
Москве да Москва Питер вот и всё а так
receive And therefore taxes immediately go there and it is
получа И поэтому налоги сразу идут туда
considered they will sell this oil and it is
и считается будут продавать эту нефть и
considered how they will sell to him and to
считается как как ему будут продавать а
whom they sell now for
кому сейчас продают
domestic consumption of Russia and there is
внутреннему потреблению России а там
bad oil there they make fuel oil only from it well
плохая нефть там мазут только из неё
look again now all
делают да ну ещё раз смотри сейчас все
these re all these resources someone is
эти ре все эти ресурсы кто-то же там
pumping there and someone is selling yes well
качает и кто-то продаёт да
it is usually domestic
ну это обычно внутреннее потребление
Russia's consumption is going to
России идёт
hell Bashkiria has good oil
катастан Башкирия хорошая нефть
in Siberia in short in general look
находится в Сибири короче в общем смотри
everyone let's do it all the republics all the
все давай так все республики все
republics will not survive without Russia well
республики не выживут без России да
let's say take your beloved Chechnya yeah
ну допустим возьмём твою любимую Чечню
I don't know but it gets 80 billion a year
я не знаю но там миллиардо 80 в год она
so and so it will get it
получает до так и так будет получать она
will be independent and will get it from
будет независимая и будет получать от
Russia
России
why because the Chechens yes put the
почему потому что чеченцы да поставили
Russians
россиян
no they get money for
нет она они получают деньги за то что
being part of Russia and those A
они находятся в составе России а те А
so they will get it just so that they do
так будут получать просто чтобы они
n't de-Bashi in Russia that's
короче не дебаширировали в России вот и
all they won't
всё
they will just return them to
не будут будут они просто их вернут в
Chechnya all these Chechens no one will
Чечню всех этих чеченцев поти никто не
return what and what about you did the Azerbaijanis
вернёт какое а вы что азербайджанцы
return to Azerbaijan or what
вернули в Азербайджан что ли
many left themselves in these years over the
многие уехали сами вот в эти годы за
last 10 years the Azerbaijani
последние лет 10 азербайджанская
diaspora seems to me to have
диаспора у меня так кажется она в раза
deflated twice the
два сдулась
Georgians left Russia a lot of
грузины уехали очень многие из России
Azerbaijanis Armenians the Armenians
азербайджанцы армян много вот армяне
keep up the good work there are a
держат
lot of them and they actually feed
марку их много и они фактически кормят
all of Armenia for Russia everyone probably
всю Армению за Россию все наверное бабки
transports money there got it look  what
туда перевозят понял то смотри какой
region then what region in
регион тогда какой вообще регион в
Russia can survive on
России может выжить
its own in the sense of national in general
сам в смысле из национальных вообще
yes the same Belgorod region lives that
да та же Белгородская область его живёт
is in short Belgorod region it
то есть короче Белгородская область она
can be prosperous yes economically
может быть состоятельной да экономически
but Bashkartastan can't yes well Belgorod
а Башкартастан не может да
region was crossed out from the
ну Белгородскую область вычеркнули из
list of subsidized
списка дотационных
I understood that Belgorod region yes it
я понял что Белгородская область да она
can survive on its own yes as a
сможет выжить самостоятельно да как
state but Bashkartastan can't won't be
государство а Башкартастан не может не
able to yes well it was removed from the list I'm just
сможет да ну её убрали списка я просто
saying yes or no
говорю да или нет
yes I understood everything means well it means 20% of
да понял всё значит ну значит 20%
meat production of Russia Belgorod
производства мяса России Белгородской
super means it means we start with
супер значит значит начинаем с
Belgorod region independence there will be
Белгородской области независимости будет
Belgorod People's Republic yes no what
Белгородская народная Республика да нет
why everything well it can you
ты что почему всё ну она ж может
understand it's better to live in a big country
понимаешь лучше жить в большой стране
than in some appanage principality no well
чем в каком-то княжестве удельном не ну
wait no one will ask you they will present you with a
подожди вас же никто не будет спрашивать
fait accompli they will hold you little
вас поставят вас поставят перед фактом
green men will come
проведут вам зайдут зелёные человечки
like yes they will hold you a referendum they will say:
типа да проведут вам референдум скажут:
"Now you BNR have already come already
"Вы теперь БНР уже заходили уже
came" not to you they didn't come to you
заходили" не к вам не заходили к вам
only on the edge they fooled around and we gave
только так на краю баловались и мы дали
them no one there  look where they entered the
им никто там смотри где заходили в
Belgrov region only in the
Белгровскую область только на
border villages there they did a kind of PR campaign like that to
приграничных сёлах там типа пиар-акцию
show and feel out the defense and in the
показать да прощупывали типа оборону а в
Kursk region they dispersed so well
Курской области рассыгнались так что ну
because I told you back in
потому что я те я тебе сказал ещё в
December of 22 that you
декабре двадцать второго года что вы
would attack the Kursk NPP and the Russians were
будете атаковать Курскую АЭС ещё русский
giving up Belgorod there was a video
отдаёт Белгород такой был ролик
called that and my mug was put in the
называется и мою рожу поместил
frame that I was giving up Belgorod and I
кадре что я типа отдаю Белгород а я
said: "Do you need this Belgorod if
говорю: "Да вам нужен этот Белгород если
you are going to the Kursk NPP?"  I
вы будете Курску АЭС?" У меня просто
just have my boss, and he was from Ukraine
просто мой начальник а был он с Украины
and he apparently watches your channel and
и он видимо твой канал смотрит и он
at first he looked at me like I was
сначала на меня так смотрел что
crazy and then when this
яг а потом когда случилось вот это
invasion happened he looked at me with these eyes like
вторжение он меня вот такими глазами
kopecks like: "How did you know that?"
коп типа: "А ты откуда это знал?"
Well, I had a whole Ukrainian lair there,
Ну там у меня целое украинское логово
some were sitting in the chief, and where did they
было одни сидели в начальника а куда они
go? I left them, and what about the
делись я ушёл от них а что у меня
Ukrainians who ousted you, yes, from work,
украинцы вытеснили тебя да с работы
no, I just found a bigger salary, and I
нет я просто больше зарплату нашёл а
realized one
понял
and a half, so I left, I
полтора поэтому ушёл
realized, so what, so what, so what, dont
понял так что так что так так что ты не
think that everything is
думай что всё у вас вообще ситуация
terrible with you, its just that Europe wont feed you and
ужасная просто вас Европа не выкормит и
wont pull you out, my God, listen, how do you
не вытянет боже мой слушай как как ты
think, how do you think, our situation is
счита как ты считаешь у нас ситуация
now even worse than it was in February of
сейчас ужа ужаснее чем была в феврале
22,
двадцать второго года
well, the fact that you screwed Putin up, that you left,
ну то что вы обанули Путина что ушли
Putin left the Kyiv region, this
Путин ушёл из Киевской там этой
Chernigov and Sumy regions, and wanted to
Черниговской и Сумской областей и хотел
agree with you that
с вами договориться что типа
Donetsk and Lugansk would remain
Донецк-Луганск остаётся
independent, Crimea is under Russia, and there you are, in
независимыми крым под Россией и там вы в
general, we dont touch you and you
общем-то мы вас не трогаем и вы
are developing normally, but Boris
развиваетесь нормально но приехал Борис
Johnson came and said to Zelensky: Lets
Джонсон и сказал что Зеленскому: "Давай
fight, we will support you, and now they
воюй мы тебя поддержим" а сейчас они
have started to openly dump Zelensky, both Great
начали Зеленского откровенно сливать и
Britain and France and America, well, its not
Великобритания и Франция и Америка ну
for nothing that Zelensky
недаром же Зеленский после Трампа
came to the king after Trump  Charles II, like,
приехал к королю Карлу II что типа
help me pull me out, daddy Charles, and they
помогай вытягивай меня батя Карл а ему
told him, "Who are we against America,
сказали: "А кто мы такие против Америки
we can't
мы ничего не сможем
do anything, go apologize to
сделать иди извиняйся перед
Trump," that is, they sent him to
Трампом" то есть они его послали
apologize to Trump, although, in
извиняться перед Трампом хотя ну по сути
fact, as a human being, Zelensky can be
дела по-человечески Зеленского можно
understood that Yes, he Wait, do I
понять что Да он Подожди я правильно
understand correctly? I understand correctly that you
понимаю я правильно понимаю что ты до
still live in the paradigm that, uh, Putin
сих пор живёшь в парадигме что э Путин
left the Kyiv region, Chernigov,
ушёл из Киевской области Черниговской
Sumy, simply as a gesture of goodwill,
Сумской просто как жест доброй воли
well, there is an agreement,
ну соглашение есть
what kind of agreement, that is, they concluded an agreement,
какое соглашение то есть заключили
can you show why no one is
соглашение можешь показать почему никто
showing this agreement if it
не показывает это соглашение если оно
exists, well, Putin published it and where, where, where did he publish it,
есть ну Путин опубликовал и где где где
published the text, not the New
он опубликовал опубликовал текст не New
York Times - it's some kind of it's not clear
York Times - это какая-то непонятно она
what it wants, it can publish it and it's not clear
что хочет может опубликовать и непонятно
who, can an official Russian person
кто можно официальное лицо российское
publish it, I don't know, well, Putin
опубликовало какое я не знаю ну Путин
showed some papers, like not O, he was
показал какие-то бумажки как не О он
shaking some papers in his
тряс какими-то бумажками просто у себя в
hands, why didn't they show them to us,
руках почему их не показали нам
maybe they are afraid of the reaction in Russia,
может быть они боятся реакции в России
who and what, what are you going to a rally, you don't
кого а что что ты на митинг выйдешь не
understand, if only  they should have
понимаешь если бы они бы ему надо было
announced mobilization in March and they would have recruited
объявлять мобилизацию в марте а набрали
half a million men there and no
бы там полмиллиона мужиков и из Киевской
one would have left the Kyiv and Chernihiv regions and they would
и Черниговской области никто бы не ушёл
still be fighting
и рубились бы до сих пор
and of course much more
бы и конечно гораздо бы больше гибло там
Ukrainian-speaking citizens of Ukraine would have died there than
украиноязычных граждан Украины чем вот
Russian-speaking ones now because the battle is
сейчас русскоязычные потому что битва
going on there in the south
идёт там на юге
that is, like I dont know, you understand,
то есть как бы я не знаю понимаете
wait, I dont understand, you somehow divide, that is,
подожди я не понимаю вы вы как-то делите
you divide people by the
то есть вы делите людей на то по какому
language they speak yes that is, you didnt
языку они говорят да то есть вы не сами
divide people yourself no well you say like this is how they would
разделили людей не ну ты говоришь типа
kill Ukrainian-speakers and this is how they
так бы убивали украиноязычных а так
kill Russian-speakers well yes well what well
убивают русскоязычных
wait stop stop stop
ну да ну а что ну ка подожди стоп стоп
and what No look wait what that is it that
стоп а какая Нет смотри подожди какая то
somehow you feel less sorry for people who
есть вам получается как-то людей которые
speak Ukrainian in Ukraine
в Украине говорят на украинском языке
than for people who
меньше жалко чем людей которые на
speak Russian so I
русском языке говорят так я
understood correctly I understood Im saying that
понял я правильно понял говорю что людей
you feel
которые говорят на украинском языке вам
less sorry for people who speak Ukrainian than for people who speak
менее жалко чем людей которые говорят на
Russian well you
русском языке да
know the paradigm of the fact that
ну знаешь парадигме того то что
Ukrainian-speakers in general have become our
украиноязычные в общем-то стали нам
enemies in the sense  and what about the Ukrainian-speaking people
врагами в смысле а что украиноязычные
becoming your enemies well since
вам стали врагами
this happened wait
ну раз случилось вот это вот подожди ещё
again look at you both
раз смотри против вас воюют и
the Ukrainian-speaking and the Russian-speaking are fighting well to be
украиноязычный и русскоязычный
honest I don't understand look it's
ну честно говоря я не понимаю смотри это
just I don't understand it's just a language people
просто я не понимаю это просто язык люди
look people speak Russian in
смотри люди говорят себе на русском на
Ukrainian and you kill them because
украинском а вы их убиваете потому что
they speak some language not like
они на каком-то языке говорят не таком
yours well
как вам
first of all uh when did the Ukrainian
не ну во-первых ээ когда украинский
literary language arise in the Soviet Union
литературный возник в Советском Союзе
again and no it didn't arise in the Soviet
ещё раз причём не он не в Советском
Union I just don't understand look for
Союзе возник просто я не понимаю смотри
example let's do it this way in
например давай так в
Austria the German-speaking population do
Австрии немецкое язычное население да
n't you think that there was already some
тебе не кажется что уже был какой-то
figure who wanted to
такой деятель который хотел
involve the German-speaking people there in something
немецкоязычных там к чему-то приобщить
one people shouted well
один народ кричал
this is not about that about that about that shouted here that
ну это не о том о том о том тут кричал
if you are a
что вот если ты
Jew you are a crowned if you are a
еврей восвенцем если ты там
Slav there you are also a crowned and if you are a
славянин да тоже восменцем а если ты
German you are a German-speaking yes yes also
германец да германоязычный да да тоже
look so you well look it turns out I
смотри так и ты ну смотри получается я
can't understand why for you a
не могу понять почему для вас
Chechen-speaking person for example yes Kadyrov  he is
чеченноязычный например да Кадыров он
your brother and the Ukrainian-speaking Slavs
вам братюня а славяне украиноязычные -
are some kind of people who need to be
это какие-то люди которые их надо
killed simply based on the fact of the language
убивать просто по факту языка
they agreed with Kadyrov no not simply based on the
с Кадыровым они договорились нене просто
fact of the language why for example
по факту языка почему вот например
look let's do it this way if now all of
смотри давай так если б сейчас вся
Ukraine spoke Russian and
Украина говорила на русском языке и
fought against you it would be easier for you no well
воевала против вас вам было бы легче
what difference does it make that we speak
нет ну так какая разница что мы говорим
Ukrainian a paradoxical situation
на украинском парадоксальная ситуация
that in fact one people fights each
что фактически один народ воюет друг с
other what does one people mean here what one
другом причём тут один народ какой один
people well look let's do it let's do it the
народ ну смотри давай так давай так
Udmurts now what language do they speak
удмурты сейчас на каком языке говорят на
Russian basically they are one people with you the
русском в основном они с вами один народ
Udmurts will walk down the street and you won't
будет идти по улице Удмурты и ты не
understand and a Pole will walk you won't understand you won't be able to tell the
поймёшь да и поляк будет идти ты не
difference between a Pole no no you won't
поймёшь ты не отличишь поляк не нет не
understand like a Pole or Yes that is
поймёшь типа поляк это или Да то есть
look it turns out that if you and the
смотри получается что если у вас с
Udmurts have the same language then you are one
удмуртами один язык то вы что один
people that the Udmurts already speak Russian
народ что удмурты уже говорят по-русски
they are Orthodox the Udmurts are mostly the
они православные удмурты в основном
Udmurts are mostly pagans
удмурты в основном язычники
no I don't know Orthodox there I was in
нет не знаю православный там я был в
Udmurt and you Well and  what what Orthodox
Удмурте и вы Ну и что что православны
well look that is that Wait look
хорошо смотри то есть то Подожди смотри
let's say this if the Udmurts already speak
давай так если удмурты уже говорят
Russian and they are Orthodox they are
по-русски и они православные они что с
one people with you well you
вами один народ
can say that yes almost so if the
ну можно сказать что да почти так если
Chechens accept Orthodoxy and
чеченцы примут православие и будут
speak Russian they will be one people with you well the
говорить по-русски они будут с вами один
Chechens are more different from us well you
ну чеченцы больше отличаются от нас ну
can say that yes that is for you
можно сказать что да а то есть для вас
one people is the one who in short is also
один народ - это тот кто короче тоже
Orthodox and who speaks Russian
православный и кто говорит по-русски
in fact yes everything well the same Mardva the
фактически да всё ну та же самая Мардва
same
та же самая
Mardva but I don't know how they differ from the Russians in
Мардва но я не знаю чем они от русских
fact one and the same
отличаются вот фактически одно и то же
appearance the same yes if you Finau yes
внешность та же самая да бы вы финау да
you are a Finau people and you are a
вы есть финаугорский народ и вы народ
Merya people who yes uh Slavicized by
меря который да ээ ословянизировался по
language that's all therefore you can't distinguish
языку вот и всё поэтому вы не отличите
yourselves from the Mordvins
себя от мордвы
no well we are just mixed with a lot of blood
не ну просто в нас намешано кровей много
and you too
и вас тоже
that is to say there that Ukraine you are the
то есть там сказать то что Украина вы
heirs of Russia as they like
там наследники Руси как там у вас любят
in your textbooks well the heirs of Russia yes that's not
в учебниках ну наследники Руси да это не
so why can I tell you that the
так почему я тебе могу сказать что
heirs are both us and you  and Belarusians we
наследники - это и мы и вы и белорусы мы
and Belarusians we and Belarusians are the heirs of
и белорусы мы и белорусы наследники
Russia Russians yes and Russians no at least
России русские да и русские нет хотя бы
not Well at least those Russians who live
не Ну хотя бы те русские которые живут
there Smolensk Smolensk so so Smolensk -
там Смоленске Смолен так так Смоленск -
look everything is simple Smolensk is
это смотри всё просто смоленск - это
historical Belarus
Беларусь историческая
yes it was captured by Muscovites when he was
да его захватили московиты когда он
only there in the 15th or in what century yes here
только там в XV или в каком веке да вот
Belgorod region yes - these are historical
Белгородщина да - это исторические
Ukrainian territories Kursk region -
украинские территории курщина -
historical Ukrainian Bryansk region
исторические украинские брянщина
Starodub region Ukrainian historical
Стародубщина украинские исторические
territories that's why Ukrainian if we
территории вот почему украинские если мы
are talking about Russia what does Ukraine have to do with it
говорим о Руссии причём здесь Украина
Ukraine -
украина -
this is once again once again look in these
это ещё раз ещё раз смотри на этих
territories yes Belgorod region there
территориях да Белгородская область там
Bryansk part Kursk form
Брянская часть Курская формива
Ukrainian relation yes and
украинские относ да
from the north people came from Moscow who
а с севера шли с Москвы люди которые
served in the service of the sovereign and
служилы служивые на государевой службы и
built fortresses the same Belgorod once again once again
строили крепости тот же самый Белгород
look what then the
ещё ещё раз ещё раз смотри то что потом
Muscovite kingdom tried to capture
Московское царство пробовало захватывать
these territories this is already different yes but I
эти территории это уже другое да но я
say it captured e these are ethnic
говорю это захватывала э это этнические
Ukrainian territories so no need to
украинские территории так что не надо
tell and look and the Ukrainian
рассказывать да и смотри а украинско
population
население
look again look again we are the
возмотри ещё раз ещё раз смотри мы есть
heirs of Kievan Rus yes yes in the
наследники Киевской Руси да да у нас в
process of ethnogenesis we mixed with
процессе этногенеза смешивались с
other growths of course also for
другими наростностями конечно также
example let's do it this way Italians are the
например давай так итальянцы есть
heirs of the Roman Empire they are the
наследниками Римской империи
descendants of the barbarians who plundered the
это потомки варваров которые разграбили
Roman Empire yeah that is and Yes
Римскую империю ага то есть и Да
Italians I understood that means Italians are the
итальянцы я понял значит итальянцы - это
descendants of the Germans in
потомки германцев
your opinion it is quite possible well with a mixture with the
по-твоему вполне возможно ну с смесь с
Romans so they mixed again
римлянами так они перемешались ещё раз
look again look what look again what the
ещё раз смотри то что ещё раз смотри то
peoples uh in the process of their
что народы ээ в процессе своего
ethnogenesis mix with neighboring
этногенеза смешиваются с соседними
peoples yes that is what happens of
народами да то есть происходит это
course yes but let's
конечно да но давай ещё раз
live again these let's do it this way the
ээти жить давай так
inhabitants of the province of Lazio yes around Rome
жители провинции Лацио да вокруг Рима
they are the descendants
они есть потомками
uh the inhabitants of Rome
ээ жителей Рима
partially yes a mixture that's where
частично да смесь вот откуда возникла
vulgar
вульгарная
Latin came from doe folk Latin
латынь лани народная латынь вульгарно
was called vulgarly yes yes well folk it folk
называли да да ну народная она народная
folk because the barbarians tried
народная потому что пытались варвары
somehow there is no one there this is popular Latin
себя как-то там нет это народная латынь
it was widespread in Gaul
это она была распространена в Галии да
yes in Iberia that's where it was widespread
вот в Иберии вот там была распространена
in Italy
и в Италии
Vitaly spoke Latin in the last
Виталии на латыне говорили последних
last centuries uh in Italy like let's
последних веков э в Италии как вот
say ae late ones these in the Renaissance
допустим аэ поздние вот эти в Ренессансе
proved that Konstantin
доказали что подложность Константинова
Darak was a fake yes that Emperor Constantine
Дарака да что Константин император
gives power to the Pope in the West the
отдаёт власть римскому папе на Западе
papal state where they got the
папскую область откуда у них возникл
Vatican that they should be the heads I'm
Ватикан что они должны быть главами я
already lost in your thoughts
уже потерялся в твоей мысли
no well what they took look come on come on
не ну то что взяли смотри давай давай
again then look at Latin and the one they
ещё раз значит смотри латыни и той на
wrote in well come on look the
которую написали хорошо давай так смотри
Roman Empire was big who has anything to
Римская империя была большая кто имеет
do with Rome modern Italians
отношение к Риму современные итальянцы
who live yes at some time or for
которые живут да в кое время или
example uh residents
например ээ жители
for example of the province of Gaul which is now
например провинции Галия которая сейчас
France
Франция
and no well you're asking the question incorrectly
а не ну ты неправильно ставишь вопрос
here let's say Italians who lived
здесь допустим итальянцы которые жили
near Rome or Italians who lived in
около Рима либо итальянцы которые жили в
Venice if you want to shift
Венеции вот если ты хочешь переложить
the situation there Kyiv Moscow there Vladimir
там ситуацию Киев Москва там Владимир
Suzdal Rostov so good come on
Суздаль Ростов так хорошо давай так
come on we as if we as  would be northern
давай так мы как бы мы как бы северная
Italy yes come on no you don't even you don't
Италия да давай так нет вы даже не вы не
northern Italy we we we no you don't you
Северная Италия мы мы мы нет вы не вы
distant provinces you you just like for
дальние провинции вы вы так же как
example London yes for example London in the
например Лондон да например Лондон в
Roman Empire yes or Germany okay
Римской империи да или Германия хорошо
look yes come on stop stop stop
смотри да давай так стоп стоп стоп
look in this in this here is the city of Cologne yes
смотри в этом в этом вот город Кёльн да
why is it called Cologne it was a colony
он почему называется Кёльн это колония
like it was yes a Roman colony yes the
типа была да римская колония да там был
city of Agripina was founded there in my opinion a colony that is
основан город Агрипины по-моему колония
you Moscow that's there in short
то есть вы Москва вот это там короче эти
all these Suzdals Rostovs it's just like in the
все Суздали Ростовы это так же как в
German lands uh Roman cities side
германских землях ээ римские города
I understand look again uh in the
я понимаю смо ещё раз смотри ээ в
German lands in the lands
германских землях в землях
inhabited by Germanic tribes the Romans
населённые германскими племенами римляне
built their cities as forts yes the same thing
строили свои города как форты да так же
in the lands inhabited by the Finno-Ugric
само в землях населённых финоугорскими
peoples Merya there Meshchera Chui further uh
народами Меря там Мещера чуй дальше э
Kyiv built its cities yes
Киев строил свои города да туда в те те
crowds of Slavs went there to those lands and diluted
земли шли толпы славян и разбавляли
what crowds no no no no no look
какие толпы нет нет нет нет нет смотри
no again no crowds  show me at least there was
нет ещё раз никакие толпы покажи хоть
no mass migration of
нет никакого массового переселения
Slavs no again there
славян не было нет ещё раз никаких
were no migrations of crowds of Slavs show
переселений толп славян не было покажи
me at least one recorded
мне хоть одно зафиксированное
migration of crowds of Slavs a
переселение толп славян туда отправлялся
prince with his retinue like with horsemen went there
туда князь с дружиной типа со всадниками
in fact a governor came with his brotherhood
да по сути приезжал губернатор с братвой
and who collected tribute and that's all no
да который собирал дань и всё никаких
crowds of Slavs show me from what prince a
толп славян покажи мне от какого князь
Slavic prince should go to a people
славянский князь должен ехать в народное
tribe that speaks a different language the
племя которое говорит на другом языке
Finnish language has no special connections with Russian at all no matter
финский язык вообще с русским никакого
how much I hear the
сколько не слышал
speech I don't understand absolutely the same as in the
речь не пойму абсолютно так же как в
Roman Empire yes from Rome yes a consul or
Римской империи да из Рима да консул или
whoever he was he was sent a governor like to
кто там он отправлялся наместник типа в
this province yes to Gaul he was sent uh a
эту провинцию да в Галию отправлялся ээ
governor and he was there the Celts
наместник и он там был там жили кельты
Gaul lived there and so they collected from them like yes there was an
галы да вот и с них собирали типа да там
arrangement like imperial yes he
было обустройство типа имперское да он
built he was responsible for state
строил он отвечал за государственную
power just like from Moscow they send a
власть так же как из Москвы присылают
governor for example to Buryatia and that's it
губернатора вот и всё
and here look show look we
так и тут смотри покажи смотри мы
open  there are a lot of chronicles there are those that the
открываем летописи куча есть там что
prince went there the prince went there to
князь поехал туда князь поехал туда
reign and to the city but nowhere is
княжить да в город но нигде нету что
there that for example there were 10,000 in short he took
например там ээ 10.000 короче он взял с
settlers with him and they began to
собой поселенцев и они короче начали там
live there in short show me where in the chronicles
жить переселя покажи мне где в летописях
this mass migration of Slavs to the
вот это массовое переселение славян на
swamp was this was due to the fact
болото это было это было обусловлено тем
that let's say Southern Rus' where Kyiv is there
что допустим Южная Русь где Киев там
Chernigov it was overpopulated
Чернигов она была перенаселена
again can you
ещё раз ещё можешь ещё раз можешь
show again can you show at least one piece of
показать можешь показать хоть хоть одно
evidence that somewhere it is recorded
свидетельство того что где-то записано
about the mass migration of Slavs there to the
про массовое переселение славян туда на
swamp there is no such thing why the swamp is a very
болото нету такого почему болото очень
good area by the way this is Zalesye
хорошая местность кстати вот это Залесье
it was called so well can you show
оно так и называлось ну можешь показать
where it was like that
где оно такой было
in the Tale of Bygone Years where show show
в повести временных лет на где покажи
again no look look show again
ещё раз нет смотри смотри покажи ещё раз
look show me you you said you said
смотри покажи мне ты ты сказал ты сказал
that in short the Slavs migrated
что короче славяне массово переселялись
there en masse can you show me where it is written
туда можешь мне показать где написано
about this migration of some Slavs from
про это переселение каких-то славян с
Kiev archeology shows that here is a
киевский археология показывает что вот
settlement Merya lived and there in 5
поселение здесь Меря жило а вот там в 5
km lived Slavs where show me come on otk
км жили славяне где покажи давай отк
open me now come on now
открой мне сейчас давай сейчас возьми
take now take now Yaroslavl region
сейчас возьми сейчас Ярославская область
show on Google a map of Slavic settlements
покажи на Гугли карту славянских городищ
for example of the 10th century
например X века
now you need to climb here for example look I'll
сейчас надо лезть вот например смотри я
show you now
тебе покажу сейчас
about that's where I live Khmelnytsky region
о вот там где я живу Хмельницкая область
yes Podol there's a good book
да Подоль вот есть хорошая книжка
Slavs in Podol yes from the 6th century to the 7th to the
славяне на Подолеи да ээ с VI сего по
9th century AD dug up dug up by our
девятый копано перекопано нашими
historians here I'll show you the maps right now there's a
историками вот я тебе сейчас карты прямо
whole book about it yes not in
тут целая книжка есть про это да не в
some late yes but from the 7th to the
каких-то поздних да а вот с седьмого по
9th even dug up this is even before
девятый даже раскопано это ещё до того
Kyiv baptized Rus here it is
как там Киев крестил Русь
tank from Dmitr there are
вот он бак от Дмитр там
photographs all the diagrams everything was dug up the
фотографии все схемы всё раскопано
dwelling was documented back in the
жилище задокументировано ещё при
Soviet Union it's not like there is
Советском Союзе это же не то что там
Ukraine in short yes now these are just maps of
Украина короче да сейчас эти прямо карты
settlements along the rivers how many different
поселения вдоль речик сколько там всяких
settlements there were all Slavic well
поселений было все славянские
let's say wait wait now
ну вот допустим подожди подожди сейчас
here's a Slavic here's an article on the Internet
вот славянская вот статья в интернете
look here we go  map look here
вот смотри вот начинаем карта смотри вот
is the Dniester - these are uh tributaries of the Dniester yes
это Днестр - это ээ притоки Днестра да
everything is populated like by Slavic
вот всё всё заселено типа славянскими
settlements yes uh Vinnytsia region
городищами да вот ээ Винницкая область
Southern Buk and its tributaries everything is in Slavic
Южный Бук и его притоки всё в славянских
settlements yes 6th century in short there is a lot of everything
городищах да vi век короче куча всего
yes show me where during this period or
есть да покажи мне где в этот период или
there in the 10th century such density of
там в X веке такая плотность
archaeological settlement of Slavic
археологическая заселения славянских
settlements there was no such density
городищ там там не было такой плотности
so you said that Slavs migrated en masse
так ты же сказал массово переселялись
in your if in your area
славяне в твоей если в твоей местности
on average on the eve of the Mongol invasion there
средне накануне монгольского нашествия
were 40 people per square kilometer
было 40 человек на квадратный кломет
density then there somewhere 4-5 people
плотность то там где-то 4ре-5 человека
per How much how much 40 people per
на Сколько сколько 40 человек на
square kilometer yes you had you out
квадратный километр да у вас был у вас
of 10 million of Russia population about 4 million
из 10 млн Руси населения порядка 4 млн
lived in Ukraine wait again
проживало вот на Украине ещ раз подожди
come on so do you understand what 40
давай так ты понимаешь что такое 40
people per square kilometer is well for that
человек на квадратный кломет ну для того
time it was a huge density do you
времени это была огромная плотность ты
understand that this is more than now there are
понимаешь что это больше чем сейчас
no people now somewhere here you have
людей нет сейчас где-то вот у вас
80 people again 40  man per square
человек 80 ещё раз 40 человек на квадра
look let's take the area of Ukraine for a minute
смотри давай минуту возьмём площадь
well 40 million you divide wait look the area of
ну 40 млн делишь подожди смотри площадь
600,000 km yes that is according to your
600.000 ки км да то есть по твоим
calculations in Ukraine there should be uh more
подсчётам в Украине должно быть ээ
precisely then yes then with
точнее тогда бы да тогда бы жило ээ при
such a population there would live uh 606 million 24 million
таком населении так 606 млн 24 млн
people
человек
but no well don't count all of Ukraine but
а нет ну ты не всю Украину считай а
only the Chernigov region Kyiv and then in
только Черниговскую область Киев а тогда
general then it was more than
вообще тогда это было больше чем
the strip above look that is then
полосочка сверху смотри то есть тогда
more people lived there than now in general
это жило больше людей чем сейчас вообще
all of this would have been populated well that's how it
это всё заселено было бы ну так оно и
was all populated galloped this tramamango
было всё заселено проскакали этотраманго
wait stop stop stop that is you are
подожди стоп стоп стоп то есть ты на
seriously saying that such a
полном серьёзе говоришь что такая
population density somehow fed itself
плотность населения как-то себя кормила
somehow itself this well that's why that's why
как-то себя это ну вот поэтому вот
this Okay let's do it okay look
поэтому это Ладно давай так о'кей смотри
let's show it now you have yes in this
давай так покажи теперь у вас да в этой
Yaroslavl region yes what kind of
Ярославской области да какие были
Slavic settlements were there in those years
славянские городищи в тех годах
here I am reading you an article that the first
вот я тебе читаю статью что первые
isolated
единичные
appearances of Slavs in  The Yaroslavl region
появления славян в Ярославской области
began at the end of the 6th century, but the widespread
начались в конце VI века но широкое
development of the territory by the Slavs
освоение славянами издешить территории
falls on the -10th century, the bulk of the
приходится на -10 века основная масса
monuments of this period are concentrated in the
памятников этого периода сосредоточена
Mologa River basin and further up to
бассейне реки Мологи и далее вплоть до
Rostov, which indicates a
Ростова что свидетельствует о
significant flow of settlers from the
значительном потоке переселенцев
northwest of the Novgorod Slavs, the beginning of an
северо-запада новгородских славен начало
intensive wave of settlement about the
интенсивной волны расселения о
Smolensk Krivichi falls on the 10-1st
Смоленской кривичи приходится на 10-1
centuries, it is quite possible that an insignificant
века вполне возможно что незначительный
percentage of Slavic settlers, especially
процент славянских переселенцев особенно
in the southern stopli Vyatichi, let's do it that way,
в южных стопли вятиче давай так значит
even because you think that no
даже даже потому ты считаешь из Киевской
one moved from Kievan Rus there, maybe there
Руси никто не не переселялся туда может
again, even even what they
быть там ещё раз даже даже то что там
say there, like Novgorod Slavs, no
говорят вроде новгородские славени с
one moved from Kievan Rus, well,
Киевской Руси никто не переселялся ну
really, look, the fact is that Kievan
реально смотри дело в том что Киевская
Rus is here, the richest lands, and so
Русь вот тут богатейшие земли да и так
on, and in order to get there, you had to
дальше и для того чтобы попасть туда в
go through this, it was
да нужно было пройти вот это оно же и
called Zalesye, why it was called
называлось Залесье почему оно называлось
Zalesye, well, in Novgorod, why was it
Залесье ну в Новгорошле не почему
called Zalesye, here is that territory, a
называлась Залесье вот та территория
clean area, Zalesye,
чистая местность залесье
behind Za  forest after forest yes after a huge
за За лесом за лесом да за огромным
forest there who went there and for what
лесом туда кто туда шёл да и для чего
if everything was here all the movement here everything here
если тут всё было весь движ тут всё тут
constant raids of nomads in the Pechenegs of the
постоянные набеги кочевников в печенеках
Polovtsians and there everything stop stop stop stop stop
половцев а там всё стоп стоп стоп стоп
that is they built this Wait and and
стоп то есть строили вот эту Подожди и и
I and I am right and I understood correctly that they
я и я правильно и я правильно понял что
went there closer to like the Kazan
пошли туда ближе к типа к Казанскому
Khanate and so on yes well the Kazan
ханству и так дальше да ну Казанского
Khanate was not there there was Well so there
ханства там не было там была Ну так там
was Vorskaya Bulgaria well also yes well there in
была Ворская Болгария ну тож да ну там в
terms of invasions of nomads there were almost no
плане вторжений кочевников почти не было
seriously there
серьёзно
such again there such movements there were
там такие ещё раз там такие движи были
wars with the Morians and there
там и с морийцами войны были да и с
were wars with the Bulgars and with whom only there was not
булгарами были и с кем только не был
like there it was just there they went to the prince in the
типа там это как раз туда шли в князя в
wild in short land yes this is how it is
дикую короче землю да
with you now in Ukraine you have a wild
это у вас так сейчас в Украине вас дикая
land there all that you have you have wildness you have
земля там всё такое у вас у вас дикости
let's say well like us aa there is
у вас вот допустим ну как у нас аа есть
evidence that in the 7th century and in the
свидетельство того что в VII- в веке а в
Middle Don there was a Slavic
Среднем Дону находилось славянское
population but by the 10th century this population
население но к X веку это население
disappears here were five  hillforts on the
исчезает вот был пять городищ на
territory of modern Voronezh
территории современного Воронежа
hillfort on the territory of Belgorod on
городище на территории Белгорода на
the territory of Stary Oskol found well that's
территории Старого Оскола нашли ну
right not Belgorod yes Belgoro these were the
правильно не Белгород да Белгоро это
lands of Rus in the 10th century the population
земли Руси были в X веке население
because for these tin ore they speche once again
потому что за эти оловцы спече ещё ещё
look look these were the lands of Rus
смотри смотри это были земли Руси
Belgorod - these were the lands of Rus
белгород - это был земли Руси
and people were going somewhere and where were they going to
и люди шли куда-то а куда они шли в
Zalesye in this they were going to the closest to themselves you
Залесье в это шли в ближайшее к себе
can again and in Kyiv there were a
можешь ещё раз а в Киеве было очень
lot come on can you show where it is
много давай можешь можешь показать где
written at least in some story there of
написано хоть в какой-то повести там
bygone years in some chronicles about
временных лет в каких-то летописях об
this migration that people went there
этом переселение что люди уходили туда
firstly we have preserved chronicles 5%
во-первых у нас сохранилось летописи 5%
of what was the original
от того что было первоначального потому
because Well on what basis do you say that
что Ну на основании чего ты говоришь что
they went there simply on the basis of
они шли туда просто на основании
excavations once
раскопки
again according to archaeological excavations
ещё раз по археологическим раскопкам
even even those which you read from Kyiv no
даже даже тем которых ты зачитал с Киева
one went there
никто туда не шёл
and what from this well that means from the territory of
и что с этого ну так значит с территории
Kievan Rusin once again from the territory of
Киевской Русини ещё раз с территории
Russia and Kyiv no one moved
Руссии и Киевской никто не переселялся
there
туда
they began to move en masse after
они начали массово переселяться после
Mongol invasion can you show me
монгольского нашествия можешь покажи
show me where it is written that after the
покажи где где написано что они после
Mongol invasion they began well show me
монгольского нашествия начали ну покажи
okay a whole bunch in
о'кей целая куча в
Moscow let's say you can
Москве вот допустим ещё раз можешь
show me again look show me really
показать ещё смотри покажи реально
show me some scientific works where it is
покажи какой-то научные труды где
written about this mass migration
написано об этом массовом переселении
just
просто
look look the Mongols Moscow Moscow yes
смотри смотри монголы Москву Москву да
they captured earlier than Kyiv how they
захватили раньше чем Киев как из
fled from occupied Kyiv to
оккупированного Киева бежали в
occupied Moscow don't you think
оккупированную Москву тебе не кажется
that this is incomprehensible they immediately began to
что это непонятно москву сразу начали
rebuild Moscow and all these
отстраивать и все вот эти
northwestern lands and the Grand
северо-западные земли а погиб великий
Duke Yuri
князь Юрий
Vseldovich died along with his three
Вселдовович и вместе со своими тремя
sons during the battle with the
сыновьями во время битвы с
Mongols and this inheritance passed into the possession of the
монголами и этот удел перешёл владение
Novgorod Prince Yaroslav Techa yes that
новгородского князя Ярослава Теча да то
is wait stop am I right I
есть подожди стоп я правильно пони Я
understand correctly that the Mongols captured
правильно понимаю что монголы захватили
Moscow but did not capture
Москву но не захватили
Novgorod and Moscow passed into Novgorod
Новгород и Москва перешла в Новгород
and well the prince became a prince so look again come on
а ну стал князь князю так ещё раз смотри
wait wait I'm looking  I did
давай подожди подожди я я смотри я
n't quite understand the Mongols capture
немножко не понял монголы захватывают
Moscow but they don't capture Novgorod yes they
Москву но Новгород они не захватывают да
don't capture and Moscow passes under the
не захватывают и Москва переходит под
power of Novgorod
власть Новгорода
Novgorod prince Novgorod prince
ногородского князя новгородского князя
because if it was under the Mongols the
так как если она под монголами
Mongols did not establish their power over
монголы не устанавливали свои власти над
Moscow
Москвой
so look again let's do it the demand
так ещё раз смотри давай так требование
was: pay money live in peace once again
было: плати бабки живи спокойно ещё раз
yes that is Moscow was subordinate to the Mongols
да то есть Москва подчинялась монголам
not just appointed once again
не просто назначалась
look the princes all went to
ещё раз смотри князья все ездили
get a label in Karakarum so yes that
получать ярлык в Каракарум так да то
is not to Novgorod well then
есть не в Новгород
who was Moscow subordinate to the Mongols
ну то Москва кому подчинялась монголам
Moskri Moscow was subordinate to the Mongols
москри Мос Москва подчинялась монголам
or Novgorod the
или Новгороду
Mongols so what does Novgorod have to do with it but the
монголам так причём тогда Новгород но
Novgorod prince himself extended all his
сам надгородский князь распространил всю
power to these lands wait how did he
власть и на эти земли подожди как он
extend his power to these lands if
распространил власти на эти земли если
the power power power on these lands was
власть власть власть на этих землях
subordinate to the Mongols you have a
подчинялась монголам у тебя у тебя есть
younger
младший
brother and you are the eldest
брат а ты старший
you have an apartment in your possession and
у вас у тебя квартира во владении и у
he doesn't stop stop stop everything is not this is
него так не стоп стоп стоп всё не это
already some kind of No  take it all away don't
уже какая-то Не всё забери это ещё не
give it again look so there is just
давай ещё раз смотри значит есть просто
don't complicate it the Mongols captured Moscow
не усложняй монголы захватили Москву
Moscow was subordinate to the Mongols went there for
москва подчинялась монголам ездили туда
labeling and paid tribute Novgorod did
на ярлыкжения и платили дань новгород
not control Moscow in any way yes how
никак не контролировал Москву да как
then the Novgorod prince ruled Moscow it
тогда Новгородский князь правил Москвы
is clear by right of ownership it came
понятно по праву собственности пришло
let's say you die you have no
вот допустим умираешь ты у тебя нет
children and your apartment goes to your
детей и твоя квартира переходит а твоим
brothers come on
братьям
so who controlled the territory who
давай так кто контролировал террито кто
controlled the territory of that
контролировал территорию того
Moscow principality Novgorod or the
московского княжества новгород или
Mongols
монголы
ruled Yaroslav Selvich who controlled
управлял Ярослав Селвич кто
this territory
контролировал эту территорию
paid tribute to the Mongols who controls
платил даль монголам кто контролирует
this territory the Mongols or Novgorod
эту территорию монголы или Новгород
damn the Novgorod prince somehow that is not a
блин Новгородский князь как то есть не
Mongol the Mongols did not control this
монгол монголы не контролировали эту
territory did not control so they
территорию не контролировали так они её
captured it Baskak arrived
захватили приезжал Баскак приезжал
Baskak detachment once again do I
Баскакм отрядом ещё раз я правильно
understand correctly that look they yes that is they
понимаю что смотри они да то есть они
controlled and the Moscow prince yes he and
контролировали и московский князь да он
other princes went to k
и как и другие князя ездили в к
Genghis Khan yes receive a label for reigning
Чингихану да получать ярлык на княжение
yes so that means they controlled
да так то есть значит они контролировали
this territory
эту территорию
damn controlled stop well stop what was
блин контролировал стоп в хорошо стоп в
Novgorod's power
чём заключалась тогда власть Новгорода
over this territory then if all the money
над этой территорией если все бабки
was taken by the Mongols for themselves the updated
забирала ээ себе монголы оновленный
percentage did not take all the money but
процент забирал не все бабки а другую
Novgorod took the other part so Novgorod did not take
часть забирал Новгород так не забирал
Novgorod Novgorod it generally you know it
Новгород новгород это вообще знаешь так
happened that do not explain to me explain to
получилось что не объясни мне объясни
me I just can't understand if the Mongols
мне я просто не могу понять если монголы
controlled Moscow took tribute
контролировали Москву забирали дань
put a prince there yes who is more precise what
ставили туда князя да кто точнее в чём
was Novgorod's power over this
заключалась власть Новгорода над этой
territory
территорией
then what well damn that
то что ну блин то что великим князем
Yaroslav
Владимирским был назначен Ярослав
Vseldovich the younger brother of this Yuri who
Вселдович младший брат вот этого Юрия
died was appointed Grand Duke of Vladimir
погибшего
again what was
ещё раз в чём заключалась власть
Novgorod's power did he take money or did he
Новгорода он забирал деньги или он
install there he also took
устанавливал там он тоже он тоже забирал
money from the population all that is I understand with
с населения деньги всё то есть я понял с
Come on now I understand in your
Давай так теперь я понял в твоёй
concept the Mongols collected tribute from the Moscow principality
концепции с московского княжества дань
and Novgorod collected tribute
собирали монголы и дань собирал Новгород
so
так
naturally but  it was not Novgorod, it was the
естественно но это не Новгород это
ruling dynasty that collected, well, Novgorod
правящая династия собирала ну Новгород
they brought Russia to Novgorod, it was
они в Новгородевил Русю собирал это
not true, once again, am I right, once again, do I
неправда ещё раз я правильно ещё раз я
understand correctly that the Mongols captured
правильно понимаю что монголы захватили
Moscow, yes, but Baskak came from the Mongols and
Москву да но от монголов приезжал Баскак
collected tribute, and the Mongols allowed
собирал дань да и монголы позволяли
someone else from
чтобы приезжал ещё какой-то из Новгорода
Novgorod to come and also collect tribute, and the one who came from Novgorod collected
а приезжалк из Новгорода собирал с
tribute from the Muscovites, then Baskak came and
москвичей дань потом приезжал Баскак и
this Novgorodian gave part of
вот этотк новгородский отдавал часть
Denmark to the Mongols,
Дании монголам
but he gave it, if you look, why did
а на он отдавал если смотри зачем
Novgorod give it to the Mongols if the
Новгородский отдавал монголам если
Mongols did not capture Novgorod, did not
монголы Новгород не захватили не
subjugate it, he simply gave his tribute to the
подчинили себе он просто так свою дань
Mongols, dear, even the king of
отдавал монголам дорогой даже король
France paid tribute to the Horde for the first 20 years or so,
Франции первые где-то лет 20 платил дань
only so that
Орде вот только только из-за того чтобы
they would not continue their western campaign
они не продолжали свой западный поход
after what the Mongols did, from the
после того что сделали монголы из той же
same Poland, Hungary and Bulgaria, the king of
самой Польший Венгрии и Болгарией король
France paid tribute and  the emperor of the
Франции платил дань и император
Holy Roman Empire also paid
Священной Римской империи тоже платили
tribute to the Mongols for about 20 years, then when
дань монголам где-то лет 20 потом когда
they realized that the Horde had weakened and could not ... And
они поняли что Орда ослабла и не мо А
what kind of king what kind of king paid, I wonder,
что за король что за король платил
damn, I dont remember, but remember, I wonder, I
блин я не помню а ну вспомни интересно я
can say that Frederick II
могу сказать что Фридерих второй
Barbarossa,
Барбароса
not Barbarossa, but simply Frederick II,
не не Барбароса а просто Фридрих II
who fought with everyone and with the Pope, and was
который со всеми воевал и с папой и папа
not afraid of the Pope and dreamed of capturing
римского не боялся и мечтал захватить
Rome during the Mongol invasion, wrote
Рим во время вторжения монголов писал
personal
личную
correspondence and said: Let me be
переписку говорил: "Позволь мне быть
this Falconer under yours lets do it this way
этим Сокольничьим при твоей" давай так я
Im not strong in geography and history, but it
я не силён в географии и в истории но
seems to me that as I remember, yes, that the
мне кажется вот я как помню да что
Mongols were defeated near Legnica, thats
монголов разбили под легницей это там
where Poland is, yes, thats one of the small detachments,
вот где Польша да это один из отрядов
that is, they didnt go further, that is, and
так то есть дальше они не пошли то есть
they went further to Hungary,
а они дальше пошли на Венгрию
again, look, do I understand correctly that there is
ещё раз смотри я правильно понимаю что
also Germany there and so on, yes, a
есть ещё там Германия и так дальше да
bunch of territories, yes, Poland, Germany,
куча территорий да Польша Германия
France, but for some reason the French king
Франция но французский король почему-то
decided to quickly pay the Mongols, who
решил бегом заплатить монголам которые
for 200,000,
за 200.000
imagine, thats the story  scary
прикинь вот такая вот история страшная
can you name this king for me
можешь мне назвать этого короля
right away
сходу не скажу
I won't tell you right now I'm not interested at all the king yes the
я сейчас прямо аж не интересно король да
king of France paid
король Франции платил
tribute naked I'm even interested at
дань голом мне аж интересно
all no one can
стало вообще никто такого не
find such a thing dovik the ninth
находит довик девятый король Франции
king of France who paid tribute to the Mongols dovik the ninth and can you read there while I'm looking for what he paid there and there is even a label of the Mongol khan to the French king this is where is it in your well
французскому королю это где это в вашем
on what site is it written
ну на каком это сайте написано
wiki
вики
reading and we have Neuro there is such a network in
чтение а у нас Нейро есть такая сеть в
Yandex and here's what Louis I is the king
Яндексе и вот что Людовик I - это король
who well he paid for several years and
который ну он несколько лет проплатил и
forgot when he realized that already Louis the
забыл когда понял что уже вот Людовик
ninth is a saint
девятый святой
so in Wikipedia they are all they are just all of
так в Википедии они всесь они просто вся
Europe look I opened
Европа смотри я в Википедии открыл
Louis the ninth mong in Wikipedia I'm looking for nothing
Людовик девятый монг шукаю нету ничего
so horde so he
так орда
lived 1214
вот он жил 1214
I see yes I see I want to see where
я вижу да я вижу я хочу посмотреть где
he paid tribute to the
он платил дань
Mongols so that's all the only thing I
монголам так вот всё единственное что я
found was Guillaume Debrouck  a
нашёл - это Гильём Дебрук был
Franciscan monk traveler on
монах-францисканец путешественник по
behalf of the French king Louis I
поручению французского короля Людовика I
made a journey to the Mongols whom
совершил путешествие к монголам которых
he called manga and wrote a book about them
он назвал манга и написал про них книгу
but there was no So
да вот никакого
Louis I in short went on the
Так Людовик I короче ходил в крестовые
Crusades stayed there in the Holy Land so
походы оставался там на святой земле так
okay come on wait wait stop stop stop
ладно давай подожди подожди стоп стоп
stop so that's
стоп стоп значит так
today wait no no no I'm interested
сегодняш подожди нене не мне интересно
because Louis wanted to establish
потому что Людовик там хотел наладить
cooperation with the Mongols there so
сотрудничество с монголами какой-то так
uh he instructed this rubruk to
вот ээ он поручил этому рубруку
go to the Southern steppes to the insertion of
отправиться в Южные степики в вставку
Khan Batu in short so that there would be something
хана Бату короче так чтобы там что-то с
in alliance with them and so there is no no
ними в союзничестве и так нету нету
nowhere that they were paid in short tribute you can
нигде что им платили короче дань можешь
find it's just funny yes by
найти просто это просто смешно да
the way what king of France which is
какой кстати король Франции которая
located where the Mongols did not even get close
находится там где монголы и близко не
and yes they scared all of Europe
а да они всю Европу
in the Vatican there was
напугали в Ватикане осталась
uh correspondence between the Hungarian king Bela I and the
ээ переписка венгерского короля Белы I и
Pope
папы Римского
again and something like where is the tithe
ещё раз и типа того где там десятина
why are you delaying and the king of Hungary
почему вы задерживаете а король венгли
says: "There is no such side, we were simply
говорит: "А нет такой стороны нас просто
defeated" again  look again
всех разбили" ещё раз смотри ещё раз
look uh Hungary yes Danube there were
смотри э-э Венгрия да Придунавие там
always different migration routes
постоянно было миграционные пути разные
east Hungarians themselves also came along
восто венгры сами же тоже пришли да по
them essentially yes that is and founded there and
ним по сути да то есть и основали там и
Kumyks Polovtsians lived yes in Hungary
кумыки половцы жили да вот в Венгрии
nowadays they are called Cumans and in
современно они куманы называются и в
Bulgaria yes there may be more yes but
Болгарии да там ещё могут быть да но
France show me with which by the way the
Франция покажи мне с какой кстати
French would pay tribute to the Mongols
французы платили бы дань монголам
paid well find really find
платили ну найди реально найди
you found some article where this article
ты нашёл какую-то статью где эта статья
I want to see what kind of site it is
я хочу посмотреть что это за сайт
you know what you need to read now I
ты знаешь что надо сейчас вычитывать я
read that for example uh
вычитаю то то что например ээ посольства
different embassies like went to Karakarum and and from the
разные типа ездили в Каракарум да и от
Pope all because uh they wanted to
папы римской всё потому что ээ хотели
turn the Mongols into Christianity yes that was it it
монголов навернуть в христианство да это
was not
же было она она же тогда была ещё не
Islam then did not accept Christianity yes the Horde
ислам ни христианство не приняла да орда
like in those times contacts were
типа вот в те времена контакты были
good
хорошо
but for tribute to be paid to them with
но чтобы дань платили им с
some tell me where you found I will open
какой-то скажи вот где ты нашёл я открою
the same article look there are such chronicles of
эту же статью смотри есть такие хроника
Matthew of
Матфея
Paris
Парижского
1247 and here this Matthew of
1247 год и здесь он вот этот Матфей
Paris reports that the French
Парижский сообщает что французский
king received a mandate from the Tatar
король получил мандат от татарского
ruler in which he commands the
правителя в котором тот повелевает
king to become his vassal, while the Khan
королю стать его васалом при этом Хан
asserted his right to rule the
утверждал своё право на господство над
world based on the words of the Christian
миром основываясь на слова христианской
psalter, that is, he even
псалтыри то есть он себя дажесалом
recognized himself as a vassal, so stop, stop, stop, a small
признал так стоп стоп стоп маленький
question, do the French know about all this, that
вопрос а французы знают об этом всём что
they are vassals of the Horde,
они вассалы Орды
well, this was done specifically so that they would
ну это было специально чтобы они дальше
not continue this campaign, well, I
не продолжали этот поход ну то есть я
just understand, I'm clarifying, the French know
просто понимаю уточняю французы знают
that they were vassals of the Golden Horde, I
что они были васалами Золотой Орды я
know, I think they know,
знаю думаю что знают
that is, it turns out that between the Horde and the
то есть получается между Ордой и
French there were still a bunch of states and a
французами было ещё куча государств и
bunch of peoples who were not vassals, and the
куча народов которые не были васалами а
French, all the way from that part of Europe,
французы аж с той части Европы бегом
decided to become vassals of the Horde, well, you'll
решили стать васалами Орды да
meet the French, you'll talk,
ну французы встретишь поговоришь может
maybe they remember, well, there was such a thing, yes, where is it, so
быть они помнят ну был было такое да где
no, show me where I had a
так нет покажи где у меня в детстве была
computer game as a child, what computer
компьютерная игра какая компьютерная
game, wait, look, come on, I want to finish
игра подожди смотри давай я хочу добить
this, show me, you opened something where it
это покажи мне ты ж открывал что-то где
said that they paid tribute  tell me what this
писало что платили дань скажи что это за
article is I'll open
статья я открою
it on some A Wikireading
это на каком-то А Викичтение
what kind of Wikireading tell me what this article is what it's
что за викичтение скажи что за статья
called I can't find anywhere that the
называется я нигде не могу найти чтобы
French paid tribute there is
французы платили дань
such information well
такая информация есть
maybe they paid for several years well yes
ну может они несколько лет поплатили
at least for several years I'm
ну да хотя бы несколько лет мне
interested here is
интересно
eastern literature the
вот есть восточная литература
Middle Ages historical sources of the
средневековье исторические источники
East and West Wilhelm de Rubruck so
востока и запада вильгельм де Рубрук так
this is Rubruck - this is the
вот это рубрук - это который
traveler whom I read yes so well
путешественник которого я зачитал да
if you know there is a bunch of stuff here well here he
так ну если знаешь здесь куча куча всего
traveled yes went
ну вот он он путешествовал да поехал
to Mongolia wrote a book about it and
типа в Монголию написал про ней книгу и
so on and so on and where is about
так дальше да а где про
tribute just this is generally well this is just
дань просто это же вообще ну это прямо
some kind of nonsense well
какой-то дичь
here they sent he paid money there
ну вот послали он там денежку заплатил
he bowed and then
он поклонился и дальше
went on and forgot most likely there is
поехали и забыли скорее всего
no there
нет там
there is this German emperor there is just
там этот германский император прямо
fear when Budapest was burned by the Hungarians these
страха когда Будапешт сожгли венгры эти
Mongols battle on the
монголы битва на
river damn what is his name what kind of
реке блин как его какой какой какой
German this emperor Richard II and
германский этот император ридрих II и
what did he do paid tribute to the Mongols
что он сделал заплатил дань монголам
also paid tribute  he
тоже платил дань монголам он вёл
corresponded with the Mongols with Batu and said that you are
переписку с батым а сказал что ты
super-duper the best ruler on
супер-пупер самый лучший правитель на
earth and if you capture me let
земле а если ты меня захватишь позволь
me be in your at your
мне быть занимать в твоём при твоём
court even the
дворе доже
Falconer that is I am Falcon Stop stop stop
Сокольничьего то есть я Соколь Стоп стоп
that's how the German wrote the
стоп это так германец так и писал
Falconer yes well the one who is
сокольничего да ну тот кто
responsible for Falconry
ответственность за Соколиную охоту
says: "I really like it I am
говорит: "Мне очень нравится у меня это
very good at it let me take
очень хорошо получается позволь внимать
this position" although he fought with everyone and
эту должность" хотя он со всеми воевал а
here he is just
тут он просто
pants frankly speaking can get
штаны откровенно говоря может
involved they wanted maybe I don't know
связываться они захотели может не знаю
there all the same
там всё-таки
he also paid
он заплатил тоже
tribute wait did Friedrich pay tribute to the
дань подожди Фридрих заплатил дань
Mongols or not also there they
монголам или нет тоже там денежки
paid money yes where where is it written I want to
отвалили да где где написано я хочу
see that Friedrich paid the children's
посмотреть что Фридрих платил децкий
king and the Polish paid no wait
король и польский платил нет подожди
stop the Mongol invasion of Hungary was yes
стоп вторжение монголо в Венгрию было да
through that just that was the
через вот как раз это ж это ж был
Destolvetskaya steppe yes and that's also part of
дестолветская степь да вот ещё и часть у
this part of the Odessa region modern
этой часть Одесской области современная
part of Romania yes all these were the
там часть Румынии да это всё были
territories of the Polovtsians there  the horde was here
территории половцев там орда была тут
of course yes the Hungarians also they they also
понятно да венгры также они они же и
contacted these Turkic
контактировали с этими тюркскими
peoples there was an invasion of Hungary in any case
народами там вторжение было по-любому
yes in this part and what does
Венгрии да в эту часть а причём тут
Germany have to do with it and what does France have to do with it
короче Германия причём тут Франция
now you can ask Alice
сейчас можешь Алису
[music]
[музыка]
Alice why not work I
алиса что не работать я
turned it off so she wouldn't
отрубил чтоб не
listen now
слушала сейчас
Alice
Алиса
[music]
[музыка]
Fon Alice is resting with her tomorrow is March 8
Fon Алиса отдыхает у неё завтра 8 марта
I never use it maybe I
я ей не пользуюсь никогда может я
turned it off and I don't remember how to turn it on by
отрубил а я не помню как её включить
the way well what do you think what will happen next for
кстати ну что ты думаешь что дальше
you next I think the French
будет у вас дальше думаю французский
king Macron I will pay tribute to the
король Макрон I будет платить дань
Mongols
монголам
well funny really come on
ну смешно правда
remember it seems to me it seems
давай помне кажется мне кажется
interesting did the Indians pay tribute to the
интересно а индейцы платили дань
Mongols like subscribe
монголам лайк підписка
comment subscribe to my Instagram I don't
комент підпишись на мій Instagram я не
know why you do this why else you
знаю для чго це тобі для чого ще тобі
look at Face but for you it's one
там дивитись на Face але для тебе це оди
two or three clicks but you support  me
два або три клика але ти підтримаєш мене
and I will say: "Wow, I have a bunch of
и я буду казати: "Вау в мене там купа
followers and I will be in a
фоловерів и в мене буде класний
cool mood" subscribe to my Instagram
настро круті" підпишись на мій Instagram
pop Andrey
попик Андрей
so let me wait for you
отак давай я тебе чекаю